<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  g-gundam.github.io  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://g-gundam.github.io/ </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Exploring Algorithmic Trading with Julia  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://g-gundam.github.io/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Paredit: Fixing Unbalanced Parentheses  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://g-gundam.github.io/posts/paredit-fixing-unbalanced-parentheses/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://g-gundam.github.io/posts/paredit-fixing-unbalanced-parentheses/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Talk about how to recover when you&#39;re using paredit, and your parentheses become unbalanced.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  <h1 id="paredit_fixing_unbalanced_parentheses">Paredit: Fixing Unbalanced Parentheses</h1>
<p>2025-09-27</p>
<p>A very important Emacs skill that not enough people talk about is how to fix your code when you&#39;re using paredit and your parentheses become unbalanced.  I remember when I first started using paredit, this was a problem I&#39;d run into occasionally, and I did not know how to fix it.  Instead of dealing with a malfunctioning paredit, I decided to not use paredit for a long time which was a shame, because structural editing in Lisp is great.  Here are a few techniques I&#39;ve come up with to recover from this unbalanced state so that you can continue to use paredit happily.</p>
<h2 id="temporarily_disable_paredit">Temporarily Disable paredit</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Hit <code>M-x paredit</code> to temporarily disable paredit.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Find where the missing parenthesis belongs and insert it.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Using <code>M-x check-parens</code> can be helpful in this situation.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hit <code>M-x paredit</code> to reenable paredit.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="evil_users_use_c-v_in_insert_mode">Evil Users, use <code>C-v</code> in insert mode.</h2>
<p>If you&#39;re an evil user, you don&#39;t have to temporarily disable paredit.  Just find where the missing parenthesis needs to go and hit <code>C-v &#41;</code> while in insert mode to force insertion of the &quot;&#41;&quot; character.</p>
<h2 id="balance_restored">Balance Restored</h2>
<p>Once all the parentheses are balanced, paredit should resume functioning properly again.</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name><a href="https://github.com/g-gundam">@g-gundam</a></atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>